טוב tov today's דף daf is ע"ו. ayin vav. We're wrapping up
one פרק perek beginning another. We're going to pick up at the
bottom of ע"ה עמוד ב׳. ayin hey amud bet. We rushed through
it a little bit yesterday. I don't think I explained it fully
precisely. So we're going to start again from אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל. amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. It's like eight lines
from the bottom. Line starts with the word פה. poy. So אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel י׳ בתים
זה לפנים מזה. yud batim ze lifnim mizeh. You have ten houses
like they're you know there's basically like a row of connected townhouses
and only the very last one opens into the courtyard. The other
ones just open into you know into one another. So if you're
coming from the courtyard you have to go through one through nine
to get to ten and ten to get out has to go
through all of them. But only one opens into the courtyard.
Now רש״י Rashi and I don't think I said this yesterday makes
it clear that only the house that opens up into the courtyard
is a problem with an עירוב. eruv. Any house that doesn't directly
open up into the courtyard does not have to participate in the
עירוב. eruv. So you might have thought that just house number one
has to participate. But comes along the גמרא Gemara and the גמרא
Gemara says like this
פנימי נותן את עירובו ודיו. pnimi nosein es eruvo ve-dayo. The number
ten gives it and the rest do not have to. Why do
the rest do not have to?
Because because the rest are as we're about to see seen as
like this בית שער. beis sha'ar. Since the way you get to
ten is going through one through nine then the rest are just
seen as merely like gatehouses for number ten. And since they're gatehouses
and they're not actual houses they are not part of the חצר
chatzer and only ten although ten does not directly open up into
the חצר chatzer but only ten is the real house and you
get to ten through these gatehouses. So ten is the only one
obligated in the עירוב eruv not one through nine. And in this
way I should say you know it's different from the חצר chatzer
because and that's like the implicit comparison here because
in this oh that I got worried. That's
not
for today's דף. daf.
But if you have like this right? So we're talking about you've
got basically one through ten here and this is the
courtyard. Okay so basically what we're saying is all of these are
considered like gatehouses and this is the only real
house. And if this is the real house of the courtyard and
that's the only one that has to participate in the עירוב eruv
even though these are real houses right? Now if you think about
it right you know in the case of the courtyard we had
a similar type of a case of one opening to the other
and there's only one way out right? And that actually we sort
of said you know that the presence of these people create a
problem for these people and so on and it was a very
different type of a consideration. Here because of this concept of a
gatehouse what we basically do is we deny the status of all
these other houses. All of these one through nine don't have any
light halachic status. They're gatehouses that people happen to be living in.
They stop being houses. And because they stop being houses they don't
become relevant to the participation in the courtyard right? We don't say
everybody goes out here so all these people are part of the
courtyard because you have to be living in a house and what
we're doing is we're saying that one through nine are no longer
considered to be houses. Okay so that's what we say that only
ten has to give the has to give the עירוב. eruv.
It's very interesting in other in other realms like let's say you
know I'm just thinking about like selling whatever it is בתי ערי
חומה batei arei chomah we're not going to say that's not a
house.
I know it's very it's very interesting that just because of the
issue of access automatically its identity changes. And the גמרא's Gemara going
to continue in that vein. But yes that's the שיטה shitah of
שמואל. Shmuel. Yeah but this גמרא's Gemara going to pretty much keep
to it. I mean there's going to have a slight variation on
it. Okay רבי יוחנן אומר Rabbi Yochanan omer אפילו חיצון afilu chitzon
even the outer one has to participate. Now that seems reasonable. Maybe
he's just saying they're all houses and who cares if you have
to get from one through the other and therefore all of them
even even the outer one presumably one through ten have to participate.
They're all houses that eventually open into the courtyard. So the גמרא
Gemara completely rejects that as a possibility. חיצון בית שער? chitzon beis
sha'ar? What do you mean number one is just is just a
gatehouse? So the גמרא Gemara says okay חיצון של פנימי. chitzon shel
pnimi. We don't mean literally number one we mean number nine the
one that's you know one more in than number ten. So why
why nine yes and one through eight no according to this? במאי
קמיפלגי? b'mai kamifligi? מר סבר בית שער דיחיד שמיה בית שער. mar
savar beis sha'ar de-yachid shmei beis sha'ar. One holds you can have
a gatehouse even for a single house ומר סבר לא שמיה בית
שער umar savar lo shmei beis sha'ar you can't. So basically what
the גמרא's Gemara saying is rather than take רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
at the simple sense of what he's saying that they're all considered
houses the גמרא Gemara takes it for granted that everybody buys into
this idea that if you get access to the back ones if
the only way you get to the back ones is through the
front ones it redefines the front ones as a gatehouse and the
only debate is number nine because maybe number nine can't be a
gatehouse maybe. conceptually a gatehouse is only something that's for more than
one house, for like a complex. But for a single house, you
don't have a gatehouse. But so that's the only issue is maybe
nine can't be called a gatehouse because it's only one house behind
it. But in principle, the גמרא Gemara says that everybody agrees that
even though, and as Michael said, it's absurd. You could have here
a huge mansion, I mean probably you wouldn't, it wouldn't be an
attached house, but you could have a very nice, big, gorgeous million-dollar
townhouse, but somehow because you have to trample through it, I mean
it is a little bit of a funny scenario, right? Anybody who
needs to get to the back houses has to trample through everybody
else's house. So that reality redefines them as gatehouses and therefore they
no longer are factors in the עירוב. Eruv. Okay. If there
was like a hallway?
If it was like a hallway? Yeah. I mean if these didn't,
that's a good point. Michael raises an interesting question. Let's say you
had something like this, right? So you walk through a hallway and
you didn't actually walk into a house.
Then I assume that they all would be considered part of the
חצר. Chatzer. Right? Okay. All right. So now let's see what the
גמרא Gemara does.
Okay. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר רב. Amar Rav
Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha amar Rav. שתי חצרות וגמל בתים ביניהם.
Shtei chatzerot ve-gimel batim beineihem.
You have two courtyards and three houses between them. I'll draw them
in a minute. Well, you know, let me draw it out.
So this is similar to the issue of gatehouse
and how that we've introduced this idea, we're going to continue to
play with it. So you have these two courtyards, call them A
and B again, but the question is not about the courtyard. Okay,
the courtyards can open straight into רשות הרבים, reshut ha-rabim, they're independent
from one another. And you've got, right, like somebody's house is built
right on a country's border. Okay, you've got these three houses. Okay.
And
so house one, two, and three. House three opens straight into courtyard
B, house one opens straight into courtyard A, right? But house number
two is sort of
like disputed territory. No. House number two you get to from going
either through house three or through house one. Okay. And the issue
is going to be- and
it doesn't, there's no opening in the front?
Presumably not. Okay, presumably not. So let's take a look. Okay. שתי
חצרות וגמל בתים ביניהם. זה בדרך זה ונושא את עירובו בזה וזה
בדרך זה ונושא את עירובו בזה. זה נעשה בית שער לזה וזה
נעשה בית שער לזה.
Shtei chatzerot ve-gimel batim
beineihem. Zeh be-derech zeh ve-nosei et eruvo be-zeh ve-zeh be-derech zeh ve-nosei
et eruvo be-zeh. Zeh naasah beis shaar le-zeh ve-zeh naasah beis shaar
le-zeh. Okay,
so basically A comes and deposits the עירוב Eruv of A into
this, into house, into house two. B comes and deposits the עירוב
Eruv of B into house two. Why? Because otherwise they walk through
number three to get to house two. Okay, because house two is
a house both of, both of A and B.
Does he reassess like we had before, since he doesn't do
an עירוב Eruv he's forbidden? Right, not forbidden, definitely not. Well, hold
on. So anyway, that's where they deposit their עירוב. Eruv. Now you
remember the הלכה halacha is that the house you deposit your עירוב
Eruv in doesn't have to give the עירוב. Eruv. Okay. So does
one have to give an עירוב? Eruv? I mean, one opens up
directly into, into A, right? So one, where's one's עירוב? Eruv? No,
but since basically you get to two through going through one and
presumably they're, you only get through to going through one, so one
is no longer a house. One has become a- from courtyard A's
perspective? So one has become a בית שער, beis shaar, right? For
those that live in the house A, the only way you get
to two, which is one of their houses, right? is going through
number one, so one is basically a gatehouse. Symmetry on the other
side. The only way you get to number two is by going
through number three from this perspective, three is a gatehouse. So three
and one don't have to give an עירוב. Eruv. They've become gatehouses
for number two. Two doesn't have to give an עירוב Eruv because
the עירוב Eruv is deposited. So when you do this, none of
these houses have to give their respective עירובים. Eruvim.
Why didn't two have to give?
Because you've deposited the עירוב Eruv in house two and they don't
have to give an עירוב. Eruv.
One and three don't, you collect the עירוב Eruv from all the
members of B, everybody chips in together. Yeah, yeah, yeah, and then
you've put it in two. So three is a gatehouse, that becomes
a gatehouse, and two doesn't have to give and the same on
the other side. Okay.
So if it's one, two, and three, they don't do anything? Let's
say there's no other houses there.
Well, yeah, that would sort of be, yeah, I mean that's a
good point, presumably not because then you don't have, you only have
one house and the rest are בית שער. beis shaar. Yeah.
So it's not considered as if like two is- remember how we
had that whole thing before, רגל האוסרת, regel ha-oseret, you know?
Yeah, but the whole point is it's not רגל האוסרת, regel ha-oseret,
it's people living in something that's not called a house and therefore
it has no relevance. That's the point, even if people are living
there, once we've called it a gatehouse. It's pretty interesting that we
just call it a gatehouse and all of a sudden- so anyway,
that's what it says. זה נעשה בית שער לזה וזה נעשה בית
שער לזה. Zeh naasah beis shaar le-zeh ve-zeh naasah beis shaar le-zeh.
One becomes a בית שער beis shaar for two, three becomes a
בית שער beis shaar for two. וזו שהניחו בה את העירוב אינה
צריכה ליתן את הפת. Ve-zo she-henichu bah et ha-eruv einah tzrichah liten
et ha-pat. Okay, it becomes the place you put the עירוב, Eruv,
you don't have to give the bread. Okay, so I just want
to check one thing, one minute.
Now, רש"י Rashi makes it sound, and I just want to point
this out, because רש״י Rashi makes it sound like it's even possible—I
should draw a bigger picture here—רש״י Rashi makes it sound that it's
even possible that that
number
two
has a door elsewhere into the courtyard. Okay, that that's part of
the חידוש chiddush here is that is that in theory—I don't know
if that's clear, okay—is that in theory two could have been considered
a house. You could have gone straight into, straight into two, right?
And you could have gone straight into two from here and it
could have been considered a house. But because you chose to get
to it by going through one and by going through three, you
have therefore—I'm sorry, not that two could have been considered a house.
Did I do that right?
Yeah, I did that right. I did that right. So because two
could have had independent access, one would not have had to be
necessarily a בית שער. beis shar. In theory you could have gotten
to two directly, right? And three wouldn't have had to be a
בית שער. beis shar. In theory you could have gotten into two
directly. But because when you place the עירוב, eruv, you chose to
get into two through going through one or through going through three,
that act of getting to two in that way when placing the
עירוב eruv allowed it to be considered for עירוב eruv purposes as
if this whole thing was a בית שער. beis shar. Do you
understand? Am I being clear? Meaning, as opposed to before where we
said that structurally there's no way of getting into ten except through
all of those. So in the way it's so constructed these things
have to serve for number, one through three have to serve for
number ten. Here we're saying that even though you could get into
two directly, since when you place the עירוב eruv you place it
by going through one. But structurally one could be independent, right? You
don't have to get to two through going through one, you can
just get to two separately and one could be independent. But since
you chose to put the עירוב eruv by going through one, effectively
for עירוב eruv purposes you've designated it just as a בית שער
beis shar and you've gotten it off the hook for contributing to
the עירוב. eruv.
You don't actually have to go through it that way as long
as you say I'm going to go through it?
No, לכתחילה lachatchila you actually went through one to deposit the עירוב
eruv into. He's now said two ideas here about this, which is
number one as I said, the,
what do you call it? If you only have access through the
back house, the other one automatically becomes a בית שער. beis shar.
And now the גמרא Gemara seems to be that, and this רש״י
Rashi seems to underscore this in the way he explains the גמרא,
Gemara, seems to be even if you have access separately, if when
you went to the inner one to put the עירוב eruv you
went through the outer ones even if you could have gone another
way, that act of putting the עירוב eruv and walking through the
outer ones defines the outer ones as a בית שער beis shar
as well. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. So בדיק להו
רבא לרבנן, badik lehu Rava lerabbanan,
רבא, Rava, excuse me, used to like test the rabbis, you know,
throw out like a brain teaser, see how they were learning this
סוגיא. sugya. He gave them the following little riddle. The students, right?
The students.
The ישיבה. Yeshiva.
בי רחבתא דחצירתא, bei rechovata dechatzeirota, ותרי בתי בינייהו. u'trei batim beinei'hu.
Now this sounds like it's going to be an easier case. You
have two courtyards and two houses between them. זה בדרך זה ונותן
את עירובו בזה וזה בדרך זה ונותן את עירובו בזה. zeh bederech
zeh venotein es eruvo bezeh vezeh bederech zeh venotein es eruvo bezeh.
Okay, so here the case
is
you have your
two courtyards, you have your A and your B, you have your
house here and your house here, your one and your two. Okay,
and it just so happened that the houses are open into one
another. Okay, and this by the way proves the point that in
theory they could be independent. Okay, so
you can get into house two directly, get into house one directly.
They each can be gotten into without the other. Okay, but since
we have just said that if you chose when you were putting
the עירוב eruv to go through something to get to the other,
you're able to turn the one you went through into a בית
שער. beis shar. So even though each one of these is clearly
independent, you can get in and out of it separately, if you
were to go through one to get to the other, you would
turn it into a בית שער. beis shar. So A went through
one and deposited his עירוב eruv in house number two. Okay, and
B and presumably house number two could be considered to be part
of A because you can, it can get to A through number
one. Okay, B went through number two and deposited his עירוב eruv
in house number A. So what have you now done? You have
taken by your act of going through it and depositing, even though
in theory these are independent, because you chose to go through it,
B has converted number two into a בית שער beis shar of
one. And A has converted number one into a בית שער beis
shar of two. Okay, okay, but the problem, but the issue is,
but does A's action, right, A's action of putting the עירוב eruv
here makes this into a בית שער. beis shar. That's a בית
שער beis shar from A's perspective. That's an A בית שער. beis
shar. Okay, but B put his עירוב eruv there. You can't put
your עירוב eruv in a בית שער. beis shar. So does the
fact B went through, went through number one and got one off
the hook? So one doesn't have to contribute to A, made it
into a בית שער. beis shar. But does that make it impossible
now for B to put his עירוב eruv into number one? Okay,
and vice versa. So that's the question.
Wait, in the question, still every time you had a בית שער,
beis shar, it was actually a בית, beis, a בית. bayis. Right?
You know, this בית שער beit shaar led up to something. Right.
But here in some ways it's not.
Well, what's leading up to something based on the other perspective is
a בית שער. beit shaar. But this demonstrates again how far we're
taking it that it's not just that the only way to get
to it is through this, and that makes it a gatehouse, it's
just when you deposited your עירוב eiruv you went through it and
that made it into a gatehouse. So what if it's contradictory?
Okay, זה בדרך זה ונותן עירוב בזה, zeh bederech zeh venotein eiruv
bezeh, okay, so anyway, let's read it. זה בדרך זה ונותן עירוב
בזה וזה בדרך זה ונותן עירוב בזה. zeh bederech zeh venotein eiruv
bezeh vezeh bederech zeh venotein eiruv bezeh. קנו עירובו לא? Kanu eiruvo
lo? Does it work? Does A's work and does B's work? מי
מטרת ליה לגבי דהאי בית ולגבי דהאי
בית שער ולגבי דהאי בית ולגבי דהאי בית
שער ולגבי דהאי בית שער ולגבי דהאי בית. Mi matrelei legabei dehai
bayit ulegabei dehai beit shaar ulegabei dehai bayit ulegabei dehai beit shaar
ulegabei dehai beit shaar ulegabei dehai bayit. Can this have a double
definition? Can you say that number one from A's perspective, what's number
one's status? Number one from A's perspective is a בית שער beit
shaar and from B's perspective is a בית bayit because B put
the עירוב eiruv there, and the same in the reverse. House number
two from A's perspective is a בית שער, beit shaar, I mean
no, from B's perspective is a בית שער beit shaar because B
went through number two to get to one, and from A's perspective
is a בית. bayit. Can it have a double definition? Okay, and
the relevance would be, since number one from A's perspective is a
בית שער, beit shaar, A doesn't have to contribute to the עירוב
eiruv for one, but since from B's perspective it's a בית, bayit,
B can keep its עירוב eiruv there. Okay, so can it have
two definitions? Now, you know, between you and me I would say,
give me a break, this stuff is not really a בית שער,
beit shaar, right? I mean you know, functionally these things are separate,
you just chose to walk through it to get there, so you
know, maybe it doesn't completely undermine its natural definition as a בית.
bayit.
Let's see how far they
take this though before it becomes... So, alright, so let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. אמרי ליה Amrei leh says back to him,
שניהם לא קנו עירוב. shneihem lo kanu eiruv. They didn't like playing
around like this. They said look, you can't have your cake and
eat it too, you cannot say it's both a בית שער beit
shaar and a בית. bayit. ממה נפשך, Ma nafshach, make up your
mind. אי בית שער משוית ליה, I'beit shaar mashreleh, if number one
is a בית שער beit shaar for A because he walked through
number one to get to B, then הנותן עירוב בבית שער ואכסדרה
אינו עירוב. hanotein eiruv be'beit shaar ve'achsadrah eino eiruv. If you deposit
your עירוב eiruv in a gatehouse or like in a patio or
whatever, it's not an עירוב. eiruv. So if we let number one
get off the hook from contributing to A because A has made
it into a בית שער, beit shaar, then B can't deposit its
עירוב eiruv there. אי בית משוית ליה, I'bayit mashreleh, so what do
you, so okay, so let's say fine, forget it. We'll make number
one into a house. We won't make it a בית שער. beit
shaar. Okay, then כמאן דאית ליה בבית ומערב ליה, kaman d'ita lei
baveit u'maarvelei, then it would have to contribute to the עירוב. eiruv.
Okay, you can't have it both ways. If because you walked through
one it's a gatehouse and it doesn't have to contribute to the
עירוב eiruv of A, then B has no ability to put its
עירוב eiruv there. Okay, so it cannot serve as a gatehouse for
A and as a בית bayit for B. So now the גמרא
Gemara says is that really true that we have to be consistent?
ומאי
שנא מדרבא? U'mai shna mideRava? How's it different than what רבא Rava
says? דאמר רבא, de'amar Rava, אמר לו שנים צא וערוב לנו. amar
lo shnayim tze ve'areiva lanu. Somebody said to two people, there were
two people said to one person, go make an עירוב eiruv for
us. ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon said to somebody, go make an
עירוב eiruv for us. לאחד עירב עליו מבעוד יום לאחד עירב עליו
בין
השמשות. Leachad eirav alav mibod yom, leachad eirav alav bein hashmashot. One
of them he made the עירוב eiruv when it was, so basically,
here's ראובן Reuven and here's שמעון Shimon and here's
I don't know, here's John.
Okay, so they both say go make an עירוב eiruv for us.
They each give him a separate עירוב. eiruv. They each give him
their own עירוב eiruv to make. Okay? ראובן's Reuven עירוב, eiruv, now
רש"י Rashi says this is עירוב תחומין eiruv techumin which it sounds
a little more like, based on another גמרא Gemara תוספות Tosafot says
it's עירוב חצרות. eiruv chatzeirot. Let's just talk about עירוב תחומין eiruv
techumin for simplicity purposes. Okay, so ראובן, Reuven, and he puts both
of them here, you know whatever, at the 2000 אמה amah limit,
whatever, it doesn't matter. ראובן's Reuven עירוב eiruv he puts at, we'll
assume, at 5:50 PM, okay, and שמעון's Shimon עירוב eiruv he puts
at, and let's say that בין השמשות bein hashmashot is from 6:00
to 6:30. That's בין השמשות. bein hashmashot. Okay, so אחד עירב עליו
מבעוד יום ואחד עירב עליו בין השמשות. echad eirev alav mibod yom
ve'echad eirev bein hashmashot. שמעון's Shimon עירוב eiruv he puts at 6:15.
Okay, then what happens?
Okay, אחד עירב עליו מבעוד יום ואחד עירב עליו בין השמשות. echad
eirev alav mibod yom ve'echad eirev bein hashmashot. זה שעירב עליו מבעוד
יום נאכל עירובו בין השמשות וזה שעירב בין השמשות נאכל עירובו משתחשך.
Zeh she'eirev alav mibod yom ne'echal eiruvo bein hashmashot vezeh she'eirev bein
hashmashot ne'echal eiruvo mishetichshach. So this guy, actually you know what I'm
going to start, forget the 2000 אמה, amah, I'll even demonstrate, we'll
make it like time-wise. So ראובן's Reuven was 5:50,
okay, שמעון's Shimon was 6:15.
That was when שמעון's Shimon עירוב eiruv was. By 6:15,
ראובן's Reuven עירוב eiruv had been destroyed, okay, it got eaten, right?
The guy put it 5:50, נאכל עירובו בין השמשות. ne'echal eiruvo bein
hashmashot. The guy put it בין השמשות bein hashmashot at 6:45 here,
נאכל עירובו משתחשך.
ne'echal eiruvo mishetichshach. No, not 6:45, he said the guy בין השמשות,
bein hashmashot, he said it was from 6:00 to 6:30.
Yeah, so משתחשך mishe'techshach after it's dark. Fine, you want to say
6:30, whatever, it doesn't matter, משתחשך. mishe'techshach. Okay, so you got the
scenario? Now, here's the question. Did the עירובים eruvin work? For ראובן
Reuven's עירוב eruv to have worked, you had to say that by
6:15, it's בין השמשות, bein hashmashos, so it's the big question time.
So you have to say that by 6:15, it was already night.
Okay, now we would normally say that ספק עירוב לקולא sfeik eruv
l'kula because it's a דרבנן derabbanan and ספק עירוב לקולא. sfeik eruv
l'kula. So for ראובן Reuven we're going to say, oh don't worry,
at 6:10 we'll say it was already night. But for שמעון, Shimon,
if it was already night at 6:10, his עירוב eruv is no
good because the עירוב eruv has to be placed מבעוד יום. mibe'od
yom. So for שמעון Shimon we're going to say, don't worry, it
wasn't night until 6:30 or until 6:25.
So for ראובן Reuven we're going to call... so what are we
going to call this? Are we going to call it night or
are we going to call it day? So for ראובן Reuven we're
going to call it night, and for שמעון Shimon we're going to
call it day. Okay, and actually we say that and we let
both עירובים eruvin work.
Okay, so נאכל עירובו משתחשך ne'echal eruvo mishe'techshach ושניהם קנו עירוב. ushneihem
kanu eruv. They both work. So you see we're prepared to be
contradictory. We can call this period night for one guy and day
for the next guy. So here goes. Let's call house number one
a בית שער beit sha'ar for A and therefore it doesn't have
to contribute to courtyard A, and we'll call it a בית bayis
for B, so B can deposit the עירוב eruv there.
So it doesn't have to be on all of בין השמשות, bein
hashmashos, just part of בין השמשות? bein hashmashos? Is that it? The
עירוב?
eruv? For it to be good because of ספק? safek? Yeah, so
anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this. הכי השתא, hachi hashta, how
can you compare? התם, hasam, ספק יממא ספק ליליא. safek yemama safek
leilya. There, that time period is maybe night, maybe day. לא מינכרא
מילתא. lo minchara milta. If you say for ראובן Reuven it's day
and for שמעון Shimon it's night, it's not like an obvious contradiction.
Each guy comes to you separately, you give a different פסק. psak.
It's not like you have some contradictory phenomenon staring you in the
face. אבל הכא, aval hacha, here, אי לגבי דהאי בית, ei legabei
dehai bayis, if number one is a בית bayis for
courtyard B, לגבי דהאי בית, legabei dehai bayis, it's got to be
a בית bayis for
A. אי לגבי דהאי בית שער, ei legabei dehai beit sha'ar, and
if it's a בית שער beit sha'ar for A, לגבי דהאי נמי
בית שער, legabei dehai nami beit sha'ar, so for B it also
has to be a בית שער. beit sha'ar. So here it's more
of a contradiction. Now, not so clear why it's more of a
contradiction here.
I would say two things. One, which the גמרא Gemara doesn't even
really say, is that it's not here a ספק. safek. If I
said I don't know how to define the status of the house,
so it's ספק לקולא, safek l'kula, for you I'll call it a
בית שער beit sha'ar and for you I'll call it a בית.
bayis. Okay, so you could sort of make your terms with the
idea. This is a ספק safek and we're always willing to be
lenient. Here, we're not saying it's a ספק safek what to call
this house. We're saying from A's perspective, it is completely a בית
שער, beit sha'ar, and from B's perspective, it is completely a בית.
bayis. So we're not giving it a doubtful definition and therefore ruling
leniently, we're giving it a double definition and a contradictory definition. That
I think is the easiest thing to say about why the גמרא
Gemara considers it to be more of a problem. The other thing
is more the idea, I think, of concrete versus abstract. How do
you define a time period? There's no thing here. It's just a
time period. So it's not... it does not create as much of
a joke, as it were. Whereas if you have something very concrete
in front of you, then to give it different labels at different
times is something that very much seems more of a contradiction to
people. And as רש"י Rashi says, if you look at the last
line of רש"י, Rashi, the last רש"י Rashi here right before the
new פרק, perek, he says, והכי הוי מילי דרבנן כחוכא
וטלולא. ve'hachi havei milei de'rabbanan ke'chucha ve'tulula. It'll make the words of
the רבנן rabbanan like a joke, ולא ניתן פתח לצדוקין לרדות, velo
niten pesach litzdukin lirdos, and it won't give the Sadducees, whatever, the
anti-rabbinic people a way of mocking. So it's more... it's more obviously
a problem when it's something actual and concrete. So that's the end
of that. And again, the fascinating thing being that the idea of
something that really is a house, functionally it's a house, and not
only that, in the last cases, you could actually access it independently.
You could, you know, you don't have to go through one to
get to the other. The other one could be accessed independently, nevertheless,
if in the process of putting the עירוב eruv you go through
it, that would be enough to label it a בית שער beit
sha'ar and to say that it does not have to contribute to
the עירוב. eruv. הדרן עלך דייר. hadran alach dayyar.
To me this whole thing is like a fantasy video game. In
the game there are rules, you know, and while you're in the
game, you play, but then there's real life
and
you can't operate like that. You're right. Everybody, everybody is subject to
these rules. But they're so complicated even the rabbis are testing, quizzing
each other. How did they expect people didn't have rabbis in every
house?
Well, but how is that different than in other areas of הלכה?
halacha?
I mean, I don't know that other areas have so many scenarios
because
spatial
things
could be so different the way houses are ten in one after
the other or two in the middle.
It's an interesting question.
Right, it has to be fixed by...
Right. Right. Yeah, it's a good question. I mean, on the other
hand, it's like when you set up an עירוב Eruv in a
town, you know, you consult an expert and then you have then
the system runs.
But this is individual houses.
I know, but it's for the courtyard. So I mean you get
one פסק Psak and then you run by with it on a
week by week basis.
And the rabbis are so confused.
Well, but that's true, I mean, just because there's debate doesn't mean
it doesn't get resolved. And so you ask, so maybe there are
different פסקים. Psakim. But I hear the point, which is look, every
area of הלכה, Halacha, a lot of areas of הלכה Halacha are
highly complex and so on. But the point being that this is
one that I mean you're right. It's like an entire מסכת. Masechet.
I mean, even if you talk about like נדה, Niddah, which is
a very complex area of הלכה, Halacha, right? Only about eight pages
in מסכת נדה Masechet Niddah have to do with נדה Niddah as
we practice it, you know? So it's almost like the laws of
טומאה וטהרה, Tumah v'Taharah, this type of thing. They're so complex and
so many details, and how do you expect the normal person to
be able to manage it? It's like SimCity. Right, I understand. The
only thing I can say is that look, some of these cases
are more hypothetical. Who really has ten houses back to the other
that you have to- can only get to number ten? So some
of it might just be the rabbis are having fun, like it
says בדיח, Badich, like, you know, playing mind games or riddles or
whatever, having fun. And some of it, you know, I think like
it's not like it's a new case every week. It's you set
up the case, you set up the, you know, the structure and
then you just go with it every single שבת. Shabbat.
I just want to say one more thing. The rabbis playing games,
if this is the case and they test each other for fun,
removes it from real life.
That's an interesting point. Okay, I mean for- yeah, okay.
I think that that is a- I think you're right, I think
that is a very legitimate point. And that's, you know, true now
as well. Like this- the whole תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is a
high- it's a very intellectual pursuit. And it's fine if it's, you
know, purely within the theoretical realm, but when the practical הלכה למעשה
Halacha l'maaseh is all- becomes this sort of like intellectual pursuit, so
then, you know, you lose the rootedness of הלכה Halacha in people's
real lives. And I do think that that is a problem, happens-
I think that's a problem that happens why, you know, the-
it's a major problem nowadays that everybody asks their שאלה Sheilah to
the ראש ישיבה, Rosh Yeshiva, you know, where they went to for
a year in Israel or whatever, not to the community רב. Rav.
And they're, you know, and because oh, my ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva
is such a huge תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham and the level of
the intellectual learning- yeah, but in the little sort of, you know,
what's it called? Ivory tower of the בית מדרש, Beit Midrash, הלכה
Halacha stops being about real people and then you don't get the
reality of how הלכה Halacha is really supposed to be rooted. So
I do agree that that is- that that is an issue. Was
there another question? No? Yeah?
I just want to make a comment. It just reminds me of
the case we had about a week ago with אביי Abbaye and
רבא Rava who wouldn't, you know, didn't make the עירוב Eruv because
one of them was too busy and whatever.
It's just right, same idea, right. Right, it's like okay, well what-
now we've been finding this entire מסכת Masechet people are too busy
to actually implement it in real life. Okay, it's a good point.
Alright, let's continue. Now we turn- now we turn to another- to
a new פרק Perek which gets us talking about geometry or whatever
into some- into some more geometrical issues. So, חלון שבין שתי חצרות.
Chalon shebein shtei chatzeirot. Now we've been talking for a while about
two courtyards that have an opening and they can make separate עירובין
Eruvin or they can make one עירוב. Eruv. So the question here
is, how big of an opening, how small can the opening be
and they can still choose to make one עירוב? Eruv? They could
be considered one. How big is it going to be that they
cannot make separate עירובין? Eruvin? What is this, like if you would,
this golden middle where it's big enough for them to opt to
be one, but it's small enough for them to still opt to
be
separate? So חלון שבין שתי חצרות, Chalon shebein shtei chatzeirot, ארבעה על
ארבעה. Arba al arba. So if you have a window between like
a wall between the courtyard, and the window is four by four
טפחים, Tefachim, about a foot by a foot,
בתוך עשרה, Betoch asarah, and it's within ten טפחים Tefachim off of
the ground, מערבין שנים. Me'arvin shnayim. They can opt then- that's big
enough that they can opt to be one.
They can do two if they want, it's still obviously they're allowed
to be separate. ואם רצו מערבין אחד. Ve'im ratzu me'arvin echad. And
if they want, they can opt to be one because that's still
a big enough hole for them to opt to be one. פחות
מארבעה על ארבעה, Pachat me'arba al arba, if it's smaller than four
by four טפחים, Tefachim, less than a foot by a foot, או
למעלה מעשרה, O lemala me'asarah, higher than ten טפחים, Tefachim, then they
are no longer- then they are completely separate courtyards, מערבין שנים ואין
מערבין אחד, Me'arvin shnayim ve'ein me'arvin echad, they have to be two.
Now we can understand that if the hole is small, that they
can't say, we got this tiny little hole between us, effectively we
can make ourselves one. You can't make yourselves one through a tiny
little hole. But why if it's higher than ten טפחים? Tefachim? I
mean, you got a big window, it's over like a, you know,
higher than three feet high, but you have this big window, I
could just easily climb over it and go through, whatever. Why can
I still- why can I not make it one? And רש"י Rashi
points out because let's imagine- forget the window. Let's imagine the entire
wall between the courtyards was only ten טפחים Tefachim high. Well, that's
the הלכה Halacha definition of a wall, ten טפחים. Tefachim. Even if
the top was totally open. So if the wall itself, what defines
them as separate, is ten טפחים, Tefachim, and there's nothing there in
the wall itself. self, the ten טפח tefach wall that creates access,
then what the access above is irrelevant. Okay, so there actually has
to be access within the ten טפחים tefachim itself. Now, I will
remind you there's an exception to this rule which the גמרא Gemara
spoke about as if you have a ladder on the wall. Okay,
right? Because then that turns it into as if the wall is
open because there's an open, as if there's an opening in the
wall itself. But if the opening is higher than ten טפחים tefachim
or it's too small, it is not relevant, it is not relevant
and they cannot choose to be one. So let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says first of all this
idea of four טפחים, tefachim, four by four. לימא תנן סתמא כרבן
שמעון בן גמליאל, Leima tnan stam k'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, let's say
our משנה mishnah that says four טפחים tefachim is significant for an
opening and less not is like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel. דאמר כל פחות מארבעה כלבוד דמי, D'amar kol pachot m'arba
k'lavud dami, you might remember שמעון בן גמליאל Shimon ben Gamliel says
anything within four טפחים tefachim is considered connected. So the גמרא Gemara
here and it's a strange assumption thinks that the same idea of
this thing like of something is close to the ground at what
stage is it considered connected that the same dimension there would be
relevant for a square opening, you know, and to what degree is
it considered a significant opening. So if you need it, so if
it's within four טפחים tefachim of the ground it's connected to the
ground, then anything less than four טפחים tefachim wide or high might
be considered I don't know like closed, like not big enough to
create a sense of a gap. So the גמרא Gemara says
would it have been three? Right. No, the גמרא Gemara is even
tougher than רבן שמעון.
Rabban Shimon. So the גמרא Gemara says, but name ams four? So
the גמרא Gemara says, well okay, אפילו תימא כרבנן. afilu teima k'rabbanan.
No, even the רבנן. rabbanan. עד כאן לא פליגי רבנן עליה דרבן
שמעון בן גמליאל אלא לענין לבוד, Ad kan lo paligi rabbanan alei
d'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel ela l'inyan lavud, that's only by a sense
of, you know, having things that are like planks being considered connected,
which is technically what a לבוד lavud means. אבל לענין פתחא, Aval
l'inyan pitcha, when it comes to an idea of an opening, אפילו
רבנן מודו, afilu rabbanan modu, even the רבנן rabbanan would say that
three טפחים tefachim is not enough to be considered an opening. דאיכא
ארבעה על ארבעה חשיב ואי לא לא חשיב. D'ika arba al arba
chashiv v'ilo lo chashiv. So even though and this sort of like
Michael was saying that every that maybe that you know רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel certainly would demand he demands you
know more than three by three but the רבנן rabbanan would say
three by three is enough enough and might be enough to create
a distance that you don't say it's לבוד, lavud, that you don't
say it's connected, but three is not big enough yet to say
that it's considered like a real access, an opening. For that you
need a bigger opening, you need four by four. Okay. So that
was just the idea of four by four as a separate שיעור
shiur from the שיעור shiur of לבוד. lavud. Now let's talk about
this whole the whole idea of the window. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: פשיטא פחות מארבעה, peshita pachat m'arba, פשיטא כיון דאמר
ארבעה על ארבעה בתוך עשרה ממילא אני ידענא דפחות מארבעה למעלה מעשרה
לא. peshita keivan d'amar arba al arba b'toch asara m'meila ani yadana
d'pachat m'arba l'mala m'asara lo. So it says it's redundant. It says
if it's four by four within ten it works. If it's smaller
than four by four or higher than ten, it doesn't work. So
it's obvious, just say the first thing. הכא משמע לן, Hacha mashma
lan, no, it's telling you a חידוש. chiddush. תימא דכולה למעלה מעשרה,
Teima d'kula l'mala m'asara, the reason to repeat it is to tell
you that it's only a problem if the window is completely higher
than ten. אבל מקצתה בתוך עשרה מערבין שנים אם רצו מערבין אחד.
Aval miktzata b'toch asara m'arvin shnayim im ratzu m'arvin echad. But if
it's a little bit within ten, you're okay.
Which means basically,
right, here's your wall, here's your ten טפח tefach thing, okay?
So as רש"י Rashi says, if the window is higher it doesn't
matter because a wall is already defined by ten טפחים. tefachim. But
let's say the window is like this and a little bit of
the window goes within ten. So as long as even though you
need the full four טפחים tefachim to be considered an opening, right,
if it was only this it would it would be insignificant, but
since you have an opening and the opening begins within ten, that's
considered enough to create a sense of access through the wall and
that it is now and that you can now make one עירוב.
eruv. Okay. The limit of that? Well even even the smallest amount.
Like a millimeter?
A millimeter. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: תנינא להא דתנו
רבנן, Tanina l'ha d'tanu rabbanan, so that's the reason of the משנה
mishnah what we taught in the משנה mishnah is what we taught
in the ברייתא. baraita. כולה למעלה מעשרה ומקצתה בתוך עשרה, Kula l'mala
m'asara u'miktzata b'toch asara, if the entire window is higher than ten
but not the entire thing and the tiniest bit, one millimeter is
within ten. Or the opposite: כולה בתוך עשרה ומקצתה למעלה מעשרה, kula
b'toch asara u'miktzata l'mala m'asara, or it's almost all lower than ten
and a millimeter is above the ten line. מערבין שנים אם רצו
מערבין אחד, M'arvin shnayim im ratzu m'arvin echad, that serves as a
perfect opening, you can do two, you can do one. So the
גמרא Gemara says that okay, had... why did you have to say
the second case? השתא כולה למעלה מעשרה ומקצתה בתוך עשרה, Hasha kula
l'mala m'asara u'miktzata b'toch asara, if it's all above ten and a
millimeter is under the line, אמרת מערבין שנים אם רצו מערבין אחד,
amarta m'arvin shnayim im ratzu m'arvin echad, you say it counts as
an opening. כולה בתוך עשרה ומקצתה למעלה מעשרה מי
בעיא? kula b'toch asara u'miktzata l'mala m'asara mi baya? So who needs
to tell me the reverse case? That it's all lower than ten
and a millimeter above? The חידוש chiddush is, the חידוש chiddush is
that even a one millimeter below the line is enough to make
it valid. So the גמרא Gemara says זו ואין צריך לומר זו
קתני. zu v'ein tsarich lomar zu katni. You're right, it's in... as
Michael says parallel. Once you told me the first case, you told
me the second case. But the חידוש chiddush is it's enough that
a tiny amount is within ten. Now the גמרא Gemara is going
to have some fun about drawing circles and squares. אמר רבי יוחנן
Amar Rabbi Yochanan חלון עגול chalon agol עגול, agul, thank you, צריך
שיהיה בהיקיפו עשרים וארבעה טפחים ושנים ומשהו מהן בתוך עשרה. tzarich sheyehei
b'hekefo esrim v'arba'ah tefachim u'shnayim u'mashehu mehen b'toch asara. Okay, if you
have a circle it has to be a circumference of twenty-four and
two has to be within ten within the ten טפח tefach line
שאם ירבענו she-im yerave-nu cause if you square it off נמצא משהו
בתוך עשרה nimtza mashehu betoch asara a little bit will be within
the ten. So there are two assertions being made here. One is
easy to see why it's true, the other is based on geometry,
the other is wrong. You've got a circle that is twenty-four, okay,
circumference, which means assuming pi is three, right, then the diameter is
eight. Okay, if the diameter is eight, then the radius is four.
Okay, is that clear that if it's twenty-four the radius is four?
Yes, diameter eight, circumference whatever. Okay, so you've got that. Now what
we have to do here, let's draw, I'll just draw one radius
of four. What we have to do here is we have to
make a square within the circle. Okay, cause that is, it has
to have a square that's four by four. And that square has
to be, some of that square has to fall within ten טפחים.
tefachim. You've got your circle in your wall here, most of it
is above the ten טפח. tefach. So what he says here is
if it's twenty-four it gives you a square four by four, that's
actually wrong, okay, which we'll get to, okay, but, but if it's
twenty-four it gets your square four by four. But he says the
other thing is that you need two of the, two טפחים tefachim
to be below the wall, right, says what is it? Right, two,
now because why? How does that work?
You need two
טפחים tefachim to be below the wall? So תוספות Tosafot points out
that this is meaning that here if this is your line, okay,
this has to be two טפחים. tefachim. Okay, now why is that
true? Because if that's, only if till the end of the circle
is two טפחים tefachim do you know that a little bit of
the square is below the wall? So תוספות Tosafot points that out
because here's the point: if the radius is four, right, okay, assuming
that it's right that this fits the square, okay, so if the
square is four by four, to get to the bottom of the
square you go two, right? Are you with me from the radius?
Yes?
And to get from the bottom of the square to the bottom
of the circle you would go another two. Assuming it's right that
a radius four gives you the inscribed square. Okay, so therefore if
you just had two below, you know, below the ten טפח tefach
line, none of the square would be below the ten טפח tefach
line. So you need two plus a little bit, plus epsilon, below
the two טפח tefach line so some of the square itself is
below the two טפח tefach line, the ten טפח tefach line. Am
I being clear? Have I lost everybody?
My, but my question is why not square it off around the
circle?
Okay, no, because, because it's not that big. You need, you need
the opening to be a four by four square. You can't go
around the circle, you're adding more space. You have to have a
four by four square in the opening.
Can't it be bigger than four by four?
It can, but we're trying to say what's the minimum size. What's
the minimum? Okay, so assuming the twenty-four gives you a square four
by four in here, then in order to get some of it
below, okay, you would go two to the bottom of the square
and two from the bottom of the square to the bottom of
the circle. So in order to get some of it below ten
טפח, tefach, it had to be the bottom of the circle till
the line would have to be a little bit more than two
טפחים. tefachim. Okay, yes.
That square is going to fit within the circle but it's not
the largest square you can fit.
I, I understand, the גמרא Gemara is going to ask that's why
I said the math is wrong. Okay. Okay, so, so it says
like this, why? ושנים ומשהו מהן בתוך עשרה ushnayim u-mashehu mehen betoch
asara
two and a little bit of the circle of the height of
the circle has to be within the ten שאם ירבענו she-im yerave-nu
cause then if you make it a square נמצא משהו בתוך עשרה
nimtza mashehu betoch asara a little bit of the square will actually
fall below the ten line. Now the גמרא Gemara says the math
is wrong and I'm just before the גמרא Gemara shows you why
I'll just tell you why because it's very easy to see why
the math is wrong because let's just do it the reverse. Here's
your square that's four by four, right? What is the, what is
the
diagonal? Four times square root of two, which for the גמרא Gemara
is one point four so we'll call it five point six. Okay,
so if you've got a five point six of the diagonal that's
also the diameter of the circle. Which means that the circumference of
the circle, five point six times three is, right, fifteen, one point
eight is sixteen point eight.
Correct, right?
A little more. I understand, we're making pi three. Okay, so the
diagonal which is also the diameter is five point six. So five
point six times three, which we're standing in for pi, is sixteen
point eight. So you do not need a circumference of twenty-four, you
only need a circumference of sixteen point eight. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says one minute, וכתיב ve-chtiv
says the גמרא, Gemara, כל שיש בהיקפו שלושה טפחים יש ברוחבו טפח.
kol sheyesh behekafo shlosha tefachim yesh berochvo tefach. Anything circle that has
a circumference of three has a width meaning a diameter of one.
So that's the גמרא's Gemara's pi. בתמני סגי? bitmuni sagi? So the
גמרא Gemara says if that's true, so... Since a square is we
need it to be four by four, the גמרא's Gemara's thinking if
a square needs to be four by four, maybe a circle just
needs to be four? Okay, maybe you don't need to fit a
square in it. Maybe a circle of a four diameter should be
enough. And therefore if it's a four diameter, 12 טפחים tefachim is
the circumference. So let's just allow a 12 טפח tefach circumference circle.
That gives you a four טפח tefach diameter. תריסר סגי, treisar sagi,
12 should be enough. So the גמרא Gemara says no. הני מילי
בעיגולא. hani mili b'igula. True, your circle would have a diameter of
four. אבל בריבועא, aval b'ribua, we need to get a square inside
of the circle. בעינן טפי, b'inan tfei, so you need a bigger
circle to get a four by four square inside of it. So
the גמרא Gemara says okay, מכדי, michti, let's take a look. כמה
מרובע יתר על העיגולא רביע. kama meruba yetar al igula rivia. How
much is a square, now this is the square around the circle,
bigger than a circle, it's a quarter. What does that mean? If
you have here a circle, okay, with a diameter of, with a
radius of one, and you have a square around it, okay? So
the diameter of the circle is what? I'm using pi as three.
That's the diameter, circumference is, if this is a radius of one,
so it's a diameter of two, okay? So you've got a diameter
of two. No no no no wait let's take a diameter of
two. We'll make it a diameter of one, okay? So if you
have a diameter of one, so what's the circumference of the circle?
Three. What's the circumference of the square? One by one by one
by one. So the circle's circumference is three and
the square's circumference is four. Is that clear? Mm-hmm. Yes. Who'll give
me a look, Paula? You don't get it? And today you got
a one diameter, so it's a square one by one by one
by one is four, and the circle is three. If the same
works by the area, I should say. Because pi r squared will
give you three and the area here will be one, cubic, pi
r squared. Okay. I don't get it. Anyway. You add up one
by one by one by one. Forget it. I don't know. It
does work for the area as well, but moving on. Pi r
squared is three fourths assuming pi is three. Oh because r is
a half, r is a half, right, that's what I was doing.
So anyway, the three to four ratio works or the pi to
four ratio works both for circumference and for area. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. מכדי, michti, כמה מרובע יתר על העיגולא
רביע. kama meruba yetar al igula rivia. How much is the square
bigger than the circle? It's a quarter. If a circle is a
circumference of three, a square is the, the square around it is
a circumference of four. So if that's true, בשיתסר סגיא. b'shitsar sagiya.
So if the circle has a diameter of four, then you know
and the circumference of the circle is 12, then the square around
the circle would be 16. It's a three to four ratio. Okay,
so for a circle like this with a circumference of 12, the
square around it is 16, which is obviously true because it's four
by four, right, the square around it. So why? So 16 should
be enough. So the גמרא Gemara says yeah, that's all very nice,
but the גמרא Gemara says הני מילי עיגולא דנפיק מגו ריבועא. hani
mili igula d'nafik mi-go ribua. That's if the circle is inscribed within
the square. So the circumference of the circle is 12 and the
square around it is 16. אבל ריבועא דנפיק מגו עיגולא, aval ribua
d'nafik mi-go igula, but what we need is we've got a circle
in front of us. We have to get a square size, we
have to fit a square peg in a round hole, okay? So
we've got to fit a square inside of that circle, so בעינן
טפי. b'inan tfei. So therefore it's not going to be the same
as if it were the opposite. מאי טעמא משום מורשא דקרנתא? mai
ta'ama mishum murtsha d'karnasa? Because of the points. The pointing of the
square means if you're making a circle around it, you need much
larger circle to include those points of the square. So מכדי, michti,
okay, so the גמרא Gemara now finally gets to the math that
will make the point. כל אמתא בריבועא אמתא ותרי חומשי באלכסונא. kol
amta b'ribua amta v'trei chumshai b'alachsona. Anytime you have an אמה ama
and an אמה ama by אמה ama square, אמתא ותרי חומשי באלכסונא
amta v'trei chumshai b'alachsona is 1.4 in the diagonal. So בשבסר נכי
חומשא סגיא, b'shivsar naki chumsha sagiya, 17 minus a fifth, 16.8 should
be enough. So finally it does the math. It goes for a
while trying to figure out if you need the square inside of
the circle. Fine, you need square inside of the circle, but you've
got four by four, the diagonal is 5.6, a circle of 16.8
should be enough. So the גמרא Gemara says רבי יוחנן אמר כדינא
דקיסרי. Rabbi Yochanan amar k'dayanei d'keisari. You're right, really we should a
circle of 16.8 would give you your square of a circumference 16.8
would give you your square four by four. When he said you
needed 24, he's like the rabbis of Caesarea, דאמרי עיגולא מגו ריבועא
רבעא ריבועא מגו עיגולא פלגא. d'amri igula mi-go ribua riva, ribua mi-go
igula palga. They say that according to רש״י, Rashi, they had the
math wrong, okay? They say a circle out of a square is
a quarter, so that So the circle inside of the square is
you reduce, you deduct a quarter from 16. And the square within
the circle is a half. What does a half mean? So רש"י
Rashi says what it means is that if the square here is
4 by 4 inside of the circle, okay, if it's 4 by
4 inside as the circle, so that's 16. So the circle around
it has to be 24. It's not really a half; it's 16
plus a half of 16, plus 8 is equal to 24. So
you add a half to that. Okay, so okay he has the
math wrong. Okay, as opposed to the reality, the reality here is
that if you've got 16 in the square, your if you've got
a square that is 16, then the circle around it, the circumference
is 16.8, right? That's what we have, right? For a square that's
4 by 4, 5.6, 16.8. Okay, they, according to this, believe that
16 of the square led to a 24. And half means you
take half of 16, you add it, and you get 24. That's
the ratio, which is totally off. So the question is, the question
is, what's the matter? Like did they not get the math? And
תוספות Tosfos says look, besides it תוספות Tosfos says it's obviously wrong,
because in order to get a circle of a circumference of 24,
let's work backwards, what would the diameter have to be? Okay, so
you divide by pi, right? And the diameter would be 8. Okay,
the diameter is 8. Yes? Yes. So תוספות Tosfos says look, if
this is 4 by 4, if the diameter is 8, right, how
could anybody think that that is 8? Okay, right? Because there is
no way, I mean it's self-evident, right, that this... that is way
too huge. That is right. That it cannot be, and there's also
even a more intuitive way where he points out that that's too
big because yeah, because well just because the only way... four, four
are right angle... Well yeah, I mean because right because I mean
if you just took these two and move right like you said
sort of flatten them, right clearly there's overlap and clearly that is
not going to be 8. So תוספות Tosfos says how could they
have made that mistake? Did they have elementary secular education? No. So
תוספות... Tosfos... yeah but תוספות Tosfos says like you know a moment's
observation shows that the diagonal is not is not the the you
know the two things added together. Okay so תוספות Tosfos says they
didn't make a mistake. He says רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan misunderstood them.
I don't know if that makes it better. But he says they
were talking about area and they weren't talking about circumference. And he
says like this, he says here's what we have. We have a
circle right and we've got a square in the in the circle
and a square around the circle. Why do we need both of
those? You'll see in a second. Okay. Got a circle, got a
square around it. So the first thing we said is that the
square around it is a quarter bigger. Okay, so if the circle
is right if this is 1 across, if the circle has a
3 circumference, then the square 1 by 1 by 1 has a
4 circumference, right? So that's what we then say. Let's make it
a little bit easier, let's say that this is 2 for it
to be easier to divide, this will be 6 and this will
be 8. Okay, 2 by 2 by 2, right, that's the first
thing. That's true about the circumference, but it's also true about the
area, right as I said before? Because if this is 2 then
the radius is 1, so pi r squared, right, if if this
is 2 across, then the pi r squared is going to be
3, right, and the area here if it's 2 by 2 is
going to be 4. Okay, so the circumference is is a 6
to 8 and the area is a 3 to 4, or pi
to 4. Okay so the same ratio is true whether by circumference
or area. Now רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan still thinks we're talking about
circumference. But what they were talking about is let's draw now a
square inside of the circle. Now I'm going to make it easy
to show you that you really don't even have to
do the math because
I'm going to draw the square this way. Right it would be
the same if you do the square the other way, right I'm
going to draw the square that way. What is the area of
this square?
Okay if this here is 2 by 2 and the area
is 4, what's the area of this square? So if you can
sort of see you can just by observation you can see it's
going to be half because if you do it like this, right
you see how this inner square is half of the outer square?
Is that clear? Right these corners are exactly half. So the inner
square you can do the math, but the inner square is exactly
half. So the inner square is 1. No wait, outer square is
4, circle by area is 3, and the inner square is half,
the inner square is 2. Right? Is that clear on when you
draw that it's exactly half? So basically he says the relationship of
this to this is a quarter as it were this is a
quarter of that and of this to this is a half. So
instead of half it meant a half the inner square to the
outer square is a half. Okay so that's what... what about the
24? What? No! So רבי יוחנן *Rebbi Yochanan* misunderstood. רבי יוחנן *Rebbi
Yochanan* thought it meant the square to the circle and he thought
it meant the diameter and not the radius and not the area.
Okay, not diameter, circumference. Okay, so the דייני דקיסרי *Dayyane DeKaisari* said
when you come to area, the circle to the outer square is
three to four, the inner square to the outer square is two
to four, is double. But they said twenty-four. No, they did not
say twenty-four, they said double, they said פלגא *Palga*. רבי יוחנן *Rebbi
Yochanan* misunderstood that it was talking about, that it was talking about
not square to square, but circle to square and that it was
talking about circumference, not about area. Okay, wasn't that fun? Let's now
move on. Let's, right. Well, the point is, okay, so it saves
the דייני דקיסרי *Dayyane DeKaisari* from making an obvious mistake, but it
means רבי יוחנן *Rebbi Yochanan* didn't bother doing the math. רבי יוחנן
*Rebbi Yochanan* just took what they said, misunderstood it, and applied it
without sort of doing the math. All right, let's get a little
bit further into the גמרא *Gemara*. פחות מארבע על ארבע *Pachas me'arba
al arba*. אמר רב נחמן *Amar Rav Nachman*: לא שנו אלא חלון
שבין שתי חצרות *Lo shanu ella chalon shebein shtei chatzeirot*. אבל חלון
שבין שתי בתים *Aval chalon shebein shtei batim*, when is this that
if it's higher or ten-ten, it does not combine them? That's if
it's between courtyards. But if it's between two houses, אפילו למעלה מעשרה
נמי *Afilla lemala me'asara nami*, even higher than ten, אם רצו לערב
מערבין אחד *Im ratzu l'areiv me'arvin echad*, the two houses can be,
can sort of join together as one עירוב *Eiruv*, they can be
considered one unit if they want. So you can have an opening
higher when it's in a wall between two houses. מאי טעמא *Mai
ta'ama*, what's the reason? ביתא כמאן דמלי דמי *Beisa keman demali dami*,
because a house is like it's filled. Meaning, you know, you put
all your furniture in the house and so on, so therefore that
sense that you can, a wall of ten, right, is not seen,
even though the wall is ten before you get the opening, that's
not seen as a complete separation of houses. Okay, and you could
sort of see that, right? A low fence in a yard does
more, you know, does a pretty good job of separating yards, even
though it's only three feet high. But if you had a three
feet high wall in your house separating your other house, you would
not consider them as separate. Okay, because you use the space more
fully, it's like it's filled. And therefore even an opening higher than
ten can combine the two. So איתיביה רבא לרב נחמן *Eiseiv Rava
l'Rav Nachman*, so Rava asked Rav Nachman because we have a ברייתא
*Braisa* that seems to say otherwise. אחד לי חלון שבין שתי חצרות
ואחד לי חלון שבין שתי בתים ואחד לי חלון שבין שתי עליות
ואחד לי חלון שבין שתי גגין ואחד לי חלון שבין שתי חדרים
*Echad li chalon shebein shtei chatzeirot v'echad li chalon shebein shtei batim
v'echad li chalon shebein shtei aliyot v'echad li chalon shebein shtei gagin
v'echad li chalon shebein shtei chadarim*, whether a window is between courtyards
or whether it's between houses, or between different second stories, attics, that
combine through a window, or between I guess a wall between two
roofs, or an opening, a window in a wall between two rooms,
כולן ארבע על ארבע בתוך עשרה *Kullan arba al arba betoch asara*.
The rule for all of them is it's got to
be four by
four and it's got to be within ten. So you see, even
in a house, the opening has to be within ten. Higher than
ten is no good. So תרגמה אחצרות *Targemah achatzeirot*. Nah, when it
says it has to be within ten, that's only talking about the
case of the courtyards. Everything, you know, other types of things that
are real used space on a regular basis, it could be a
higher window. גמרא *Gemara* says והא אחד לי תנא *V'ha echad li
tana*, it says whether this, whether this, whether this, it all has
to be four by four within ten. So תרגמה אארבע על ארבע
*Targemah aarba al arba*. What it means is all those windows have
to be four by four. But the idea that it has to
be within ten, it's a real stretch of the language of the
ברייתא *Braisa*, but the idea it has to be within ten is
by the courtyards. Houses, it's true you need four by four, but
again, and you really understand the logic, even a higher up opening
still does more to combine the two separate, you know, two separate
rooms or two separate houses than it would in the case of
a courtyard. Okay, and I guess let's read one more case. בעי
מיניה רב אבא מרב נחמן *Ba'ei minei Rav Abba me'Rav Nachman*. Rav
Abba asked Rav Nachman: לול הפתוח מן הבית לעליה *Lul hapatuach min
habayit l'aliya*, you've basically got a trapdoor up into your attic. Okay,
people live in the attic, so you have a ceiling opening, not
a window in the wall, a window in the ceiling. צריך סולם
קבוע להתירו או אין צריך סולם קבוע להתירו *Tzarich sulam kavua l'hattiro
o ein tzarich sulam kavua l'hattiro*. So he assumes that if you
want to combine the two, since you can't get to that, you
know, thing without a ladder, you cannot consider those two combined unless
you have a fixed, unless you have a ladder. And his whole
question was: Can it be a temporary ladder, like a ladder you
move there when you need it, or do you need a fixed
ladder in order to consider them one space? Okay, so that was
his question. הני מילי מן הצד *Hani mili mintzad*, when do I
say that the house is like it's full and even a high
window can connect two rooms or two houses? That's on the wall.
אבל באמצע *Aval be'emtza*, in the middle of the roof, לא *lo*,
I would not say that that creates an easy sense of access,
so in the roof shouldn't work. או דילמא לא שנא *O dilma
lo shana*, or should I say it doesn't matter? אמר ליה *Amar
lei*, אין צריך *ein tzarich*, you don't need to have a fixed,
a fixed, a fixed, what do you call it, ladder. Okay? Yes,
even in, even in the roof, it combines the
two rooms. So סבר מינה *Savar minah*, he assumed סולם קבוע הוא
דאין צריך *Sulam kavua hu d'ein tzarich*, it doesn't need a fixed
ladder. הא סולם עראי צריך *Ha sulam arai tzarich*, it would at
least need like a temporary movable ladder, a temporary ladder, because give
me a break, it's in the roof. How could you consider them
combined if you don't have an accessible ladder? So איתמר *Itmar*, it
was taught, אמר רב יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef*... אמר רב יוסף בר
מניומי אמר רב נחמן אחד סולם קבוע ואחד סולם עראי אינו צריך.
echad sulam kavua ve-echad sulam arai eino tzarich. Whether temporary, whether fixed,
you do not need a ladder. So although you need the window,
the opening to be low to courtyards, because courtyards you don't have
as much usage, in a house, any height combined, even if it's
in the ceiling and even without a ladder, we're saying that would
be sufficient to combine the rooms as long as it's four by
four. Okay.